Inventory of the American Committee to Keep Biafra Alive collection, 1967-1970
Hoover Institution Archives
American Committee to Keep Biafra Alive collection
1967-1970
71031
Hoover Institution Archives
8 manuscript boxes, 2 motion picture film reels, 2 phonorecords (3.2 linear feet)
Ephemeral publications of private governmental organizations, including the United States Agency for International Development, the government of the Republic of Biafra, and the government of the Federal Republic of Nigeria; press releases from the United States Department of State, American congressmen, and Markpress, the Biafran Overseas Press Division; clippings; periodical literature; and audio-visual materials relating to the Nigerian Civil War of 1967 to 1970. Collected by the St. Louis chapter of the American Committee to Keep Biafra Alive.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1971.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical note
The American Committee to Keep Biafra Alive was an organization created to inform Americans of the conditions in Biafra during the Nigerian Civil War of 1967 to 1970.
Scope and Content of Collection
Ephemeral publications of private governmental organizations, including the United States Agency for International Development, the government of the Republic of Biafra, and the government of the Federal Republic of Nigeria; press releases from the United States Department of State, American congressmen, and Markpress, the Biafran Overseas Press Division; clippings; periodical literature; and audio-visual materials relating to the Nigerian Civil War of 1967 to 1970. Collected by the St. Louis chapter of the American Committee to Keep Biafra Alive.
American Committee to Keep Biafra Alive.; Motion pictures.; Nigeria--History--Civil War, 1967-1970.; Phonorecords.
- Correspondence, 1968-1970
  - Anyanwu, Don U., 1968 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - B'nai B'rith, 1970 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Barnes, James, B., 1969 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Binder, Gene, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Buxbaum, Richard M., 1969 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Canadian Red Cross Society, 1968 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Catholic Relief Services, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Catton, Cliff, 1970 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Comité central de la Croix-Rouge suédoise, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Duncan, Nancy J., undated (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Dur, Susan and Holly Chinery, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Nwagbara, Chidi, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Fletcher, T.H.G., 1969 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Hammond, Jerry, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Harless, Roger A. and Don Borrie, undated (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Langle, Ellen, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Mann, Eileen, L., 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Mansfield, Lawrence F., 1970 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Mercer, Karen, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Nigeria Committee of Northern California, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Swedish Biafra Committee, undated (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Weiler, Hans, 1968 (Box-folder 1: 22)
- Subject File, 1967-1970
  - "An Address to the Nation by His Excellency General C. Odumegwu Ojukwy, Head of the State and Commander-in-Chief of the Armed Forces, Republic of Biafra,", 1969 (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - Africa Today, "Biafra - The Politics of Saving Lives," Shepherd, George W., Jr., undated (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - Africa Report, "From Nixon to Nixon: Is America's Outmoded Policy Towards a Changing Africa About to Cross a New Frontier?," Wellestein, Immanuel, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - Africa Today, "Nigeria & Biafra," Jevid, Steven, undated (Box-folder 1: 26)
  - Africa Report, "The Nigerian Civil War,", 1969-1970 (Box-folder 1: 27)
  - Africa Report, "Out of Africa,", 1969 (Box-folder 1: 28)
  - Africa Report, "Three Novels, A History and a Do-it-yourself Guide to Coup Making,", 1969 (Box-folder 1: 29)
  - Africa Report, "The U.S. and the Biafra War," Sklar, Richard L., 1969 (Box-folder 1: 30)
  - American Committee on Africa (ACOA) Food Memo, 1968 (Box-folder 1: 31)
  - Africa Concern Committee, 1967 (Box-folder 1: 32)
  - American Red Cross News Service, undated (Box-folder 1: 34)
  - Bay Area Committee to Save Biafran Children, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 35)
  - Biafra: A Documentary Film, undated (Box-folder 1: 37)
  - Biafra: History of The Conflict, undated (Box-folder 1: 38)
  - Biafra - The Issue Is Massacre, Shepherd, George W., Jr., undated (Box-folder 1: 39)
  - Biafra: Lifeline, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 40)
  - "Biafra: Press Conference Given by the President of The Republic of Ivory Coast,", 1968 (Box-folder 1: 42)
  - Biafra Rehabilitation Commission, "Nutritional Needs of Refugees in Biafra,", 1969 (Box-folder 1: 42)
  - Biafra Rehabilitation Commission, "Office and Operational Requirements,", 1969 (Box-folder 1: 43)
  - Biafra Rehabilitation Commission, "Some Refugee Projects,", 1969 (Box-folder 1: 44)
  - The Biafra Secession, Diamond, Stanley, undated (Box-folder 1: 45)
  - Biafra Students Union (Abidjan Branch), 1970 (Box-folder 1: 46)
  - "The Biafran Illusion: Fate and Future of the non-Ibo Peoples in the Eastern States of Nigera,", undated (Box-folder 1: 47)
  - "Biafran Memo," Keil, Clarks, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 48)
  - Biafra newsletters, 1968 (Box-folder 1: 49)
  - "Biafran Students Association of Northern California, Information Bulletin," nos. 1-4, undated (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - "The Bill Fields Show," no. 52, transcript of Peter Udoh, Charge d'Affaires of the Nigerian Embassy in Washington, D.C., 1970 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Britain - Biafra Association, undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - British Hyprocrisy in Rhodesia and Biafra, 1968 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - "A Call for United States Recognition of Biafra,", 1969 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Catholic-Protestant Biafra Relief Program, 1968 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - "Causes of The War Against Biafra,", undated (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - "The Children's War," Doran, Dermot, undated (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - The Clearing House for Nigeria/Biafra Information, 1968-1970 (Box-folder 2: 9-10)
  - Coalition of Citizens Committees on the Nigeria/Biafra Crisis, 1969 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - The Episcopalian, "The Agony of Biafra,", 1969 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - "An Evening for Biafra,", 1969 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - First International Conference on Biafra, 1968 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Food for Biafra Committee, 1968 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - From the book, Path to Nigerian Freedom, Awolowo, Obafemi, undated (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Government of the Republic of Biafra, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - "International Observer Report: Nigeria,", 1969 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - "The Involvement of Certain Religious Organizations in Nigeria's Civil Conflicts," text of address by Joseph Taraka, 1969 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - "It Is Time for the Sleeping Nations to Wake Up and Recognize Biafra,", undated (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Joint Afro Committee on Biafra, 1969 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Joint Church Aid - U.S.A., Inc. news release, 1969 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - "Justice for All: Life, Liberty and the Pursuit of Happiness," Biafra Students Association in the Americas, undated (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Kansas City Committee for Biafra-Nigeria Relief, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Keeping An Eye On Former Biafra, 1970 (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - The Lancet, "Special Article: Nigeria,", 1969 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Letter to the editor, undated (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Library of Congress, "Biafra: A Chronology of Developments,", 1968-1969 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Markpress News Feature Service, "Biafran Overseas Press Division,", 1969 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - "The Medical Support Program for Biafra - Nigeria,", undated (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - "The Meeting of the Nigerian Military Leaders,", 1967 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - "This Message Was Cabled to All the World's Leaders," poster, undated (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - National Council of Churches Africa Department: Nigeria, 1967 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - "The New Leader," Kwitny, Jonathan, undated (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - "Nigeria: The End of a Tragedy,", undated (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - "Nigeria/Biafra: Background to War," Sanger, Clyde, undated (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - "Nigeria/Biafra Programs of Assistance of U.S. Non-profit Organizations,", 1969 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - Nigeria vs. Biafra, "Paper Number 2: Reports on Oil,", 1967-1969 (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - "The Nigerian Civil War,", undated (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - Nigeria International Observer Teams Report, 1968 (Box-folder 4: 15)
  - "Nutritional/Health Situation,", undated (Box-folder 4: 16)
  - "Observer Team to Nigeria,", 1968 (Box-folder 4: 17)
  - Office of the Special Representative, Republic of Biafra, 1969 (Box-folder 4: 18)
  - Operation Outrage Conference transcript, 1969 (Box-folder 4: 19)
  - Operation Outrage, Inc., 1969 (Box-folder 4: 20)
  - "A Preliminary List of Federal Nigerian Pamphlets Related to the Struggle with the Ojukw Regime," Davis, Morris, undated (Box-folder 4: 21)
  - "Re-assessment of the Nigerian Relief Problem,", 1970 (Box-folder 4: 22)
  - "Report on the Condition Within Biafra," McHugh, Joseph, 1969 (Box-folder 4: 23)
  - The Ripon Society, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 4: 24)
  - Saint Louis Committee to Keep Biafra Alive, 1968-1970 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Save Our Lives/Nigerians-Biafrans, 1969 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - "The Secessionist Regime and The Non-Ibo 'Minorities' in the East of Nigeria,", 1968 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Spotlight on Africa, "Biafra Hangs On,", 1967 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - State of Washington, "Senate Resolution 1969 - EX. 10," (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Statement by Hyman Bookbinder, Washington Representative of the American Jewish Committee, 1968 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Statement by Dr. Kenneth O. Dike, Roving Ambassadar of the Government of Biafra, 1969 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Statement by Dr. Okoi Arikpo, Commissioner of External Affairs and Leader of Nigerian Delegation to the 23rd Session of the U.N. General Assembly, 1968 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - Susan Garth, Biafran Babies' Appeal, 1968 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Text of speech delivered by Chief Anthnoy Enahoro, Nigeria's Commissioner for Information and Labor,", 1969 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - Text of statement Issued in Paris by H.E., General C. Odumegwu Ojukwu, Head of State of the Republic of Biafra, 1970 (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - Text of the resolution unanimously adopted by the graduates of the several colleges and universities of the U.S. and Canada assembled in Enugu, 1967 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - "The Top of the News with Fulton Lewis III,", 1968-1969 (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - "The True Foundation for African Unity,", 1969 (Box-folder 5: 14)
  - "Twin Circle Headline: Biafra,", undated (Box-folder 5: 15)
  - "U.N. Secretary-General Speaks on Nigeria,", 1969 (Box-folder 5: 16)
  - "United Nigeria Group,", 1969 (Box-folder 5: 17)
  - U.S. Congress and Senate, 1968-1970 (Box-folder 5: 18)
  - U.S. Voluntary Agencies, "Nigeria - Biafra Civil Strife Victims,", 1969 (Box-folder 5: 19)
  - "The War in Nigeria," Alexander, H.F., undated (Box-folder 5: 20)
  - Washington Notes on Africa, "Biafra Policy,", undated (Box-folder 5: 21)
  - West Africa, 1969 (Box-folder 5: 22)
  - "Why We Urge You to Recognize Biafra,", undated (Box-folder 5: 23)
  - World Council of Churches Document no. 55, undated (Box-folder 5: 24)
- Printed Matter, 1967-1970
  - Africa Concern Limited, 1969 (Box-folder 5: 25)
  - Africa Today, "The Biafra Secession," Diamond, Stanley, 1967 (Box-folder 5: 26)
  - African Research Bulletin, 1967 (Box-folder 5: 27)
  - The African Scholar, "Focus on Biafra,", 1968 (Box-folder 5: 28)
  - Afrique Express, 1968 (Box-folder 5: 29)
  - America, "Report from Biafra," McLaughlin, John, 1969 (Box-folder 5: 30)
  - American Catholic Overseas Aid Fund, undated (Box-folder 5: 31)
  - American Committte to Keep Biafra Alive, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 5: 32)
  - The American Jewish Emergency Effort for Biafra Relief, undated (Box-folder 5: 33)
  - "Appeal to All Ibos, Efiks, Ekois, Ibibios, Ijaws and All Other Nigerians,", undated (Box-folder 5: 34)
  - Biafra International Foundation, 1970 (Box-folder 5: 35)
  - "Biafra Has Oil as Well as Starving Children," Jervis, Steven, undated (Box-folder 5: 36)
  - Biafra Lifeline vol. 1, no. 8, undated (Box-folder 5: 37)
  - Biafra Relief Services Foundation, undated (Box-folder 5: 38)
  - "Biafra Review,", 1970 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - "Biafra: Témoignages - Prises de Position,", 1969 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - "Biafra Times,", 1968 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - "Biafra Independence: The United Republic of Tanzania Presents a Pan-African Viewpoint,", 1968 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - Canadian Weekly Bulletin, "Withdrawal of Relief Airlift from Nigeria," vol. 24, no. 1, 1969 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - "Case for Recognition of Biafra," statement by the government of the United Republic of Tanzania, 1968 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Catholic Relief Services, brochures and pamphets, 1968 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Catholic Relief Services, press releases, 1968-1970 (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - Catholic Relief Services Quarterly Information Bulletin, special issue: "Nigeria/Biafra," nos. 1 and 2, 1968 (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - Catholic Relief Services, United States Catholic Conference Inc., 1968 (Box-folder 6: 10)
  - Cathwel Chronicler, 1968 (Box-folder 6: 11)
  - "Christian Council of Nigeria Relief and Reconciliation in Nigerian Crisis,", 1970 (Box-folder 6: 12)
  - Church World Service, undated (Box-folder 6: 13)
  - The Coalition of Citizens Committees on the Nigerian/Biafran Crisis, 1969 (Box-folder 6: 14)
  - "The Collapse of a Rebellion and Prospects of Lasting Peace,", undated (Box-folder 6: 15)
  - Correspondence, "Biafra Reply," Jervis, Steven, undated (Box-folder 6: 16)
  - "Cry Justice!," Segun, F.O., undated (Box-folder 6: 17)
  - Diakonisches Werk, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 6: 18)
  - Emergency Committee on Nigeria and Biafra, 1969 (Box-folder 6: 19)
  - "Emergency Relief for Nigerial Biafra: A Committee of Concerned Citizens,", undated (Box-folder 6: 20)
  - Extracts from British Parliamentary debates on the Nigerian situation in the House of Commons, 1968 (Box-folder 6: 21)
  - Friends International Centre, Centre Quaker International, 1968 (Box-folder 6: 22)
  - Hearing before the Subcommittee on African Affairs, "Nigerian-Biafran Relief Situation,", 1968 (Box-folder 6: 23)
  - History of the 20th Century: Our World Today, "The Biafran Tragedy,", 1967 (Box-folder 6: 24)
  - House Congressional Resolution nos. 96-100, 107, 127, 1969 (Box-folder 6: 25)
  - "I Believe in One Nigeria - Zik,", undated (Box-folder 6: 26)
  - "Ibos in a United Nigeria,", undated (Box-folder 6: 27)
  - "Imaginary Biafra," Eshiett, Sunday U., 1969 (Box-folder 6: 28)
  - International Conscience in Action, 1970 (Box-folder 6: 29)
  - "An Interview with General Gowon,", 1969 (Box-folder 6: 30)
  - The Kansas Month of Hope for the Children of Biafra/Nigeria, 1968 (Box-folder 6: 31)
  - The Liberator, "Biafra: While America Sleeps,", 1969 (Box-folder 6: 32)
  - Manion Forum, 1969 (Box-folder 6: 33)
  - "News from Nigeria," issued by the Embassy of Nigeria, Washington, D.C., 1969 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, "Biafra War, 1968-1970," (Box-folder 7: 2)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - "The Nigeria/Biafra Conflict: British Involvement,", undated (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - "Nigeria: Its Politics and the Civil War," Okoh, Gim, 1968 (Box-folder 7: 5)
  - Nigeria Notes, "Reports from The East,", 1970 (Box-folder 7: 6)
  - "Nigerian Crisis: The Root Cause,", undated (Box-folder 7: 7)
  - "Nigerian Economy Hits a Bad Patch,", undated (Box-folder 7: 8)
  - "Nigerian Records" and other publications issued by the Embassy of Nigeria, Washington, D.C., 1968 (Box-folder 7: 9)
  - "Nigerian Students Abroad," statement by the Federal Government of Nigeria, undated (Box-folder 7: 10)
  - Nigerian and U.S. newspaper clippings, 1966-1969 (Box-folder 7: 11)
  - "Ojukwu's Government Is the People's Government,", undated (Box-folder 7: 12)
  - "Peace News,", 1968-1970 (Box-folder 7: 13)
  - Press release by the Embassy of Nigeria, Cairo, Egypt, 1968 (Box-folder 7: 14)
  - Quaker Service, Nigeria Reports nos. 2-5, 7-9, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 7: 15)
  - Quaker Service, North Central Regional Edition, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 7: 16)
  - Religious News Service, 1968 (Box-folder 7: 17)
  - "Report of Special Factfinding Mission to Nigeria,", 1969 (Box-folder 7: 18)
  - "Resurgence Journal of The Fourth World,", 1970 (Box-folder 7: 19)
  - Senate Congressional Resolutions nos. 3 and 415, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 7: 20)
  - "South Africa's Visible and Invisible Aid to Nigerian Rebels,", undated (Box-folder 7: 21)
  - "The Struggle for Survival,", undated (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - "Synagogue Council of America," press release, 1968 (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - Transition 36, "Chinua Achebe on Biafra,", undated (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Transition 36, "Why I Left Nigeria," Enahoro, Peter, undated (Box-folder 8: 4)
  - Transition 36, "Why I Am a Federalist," Asika, U.A., undated (Box-folder 8: 5)
  - "Understanding the Nigerian Crisis,", 1968 (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - "United Nigeria Means United Africa,", undated (Box-folder 8: 7)
  - United States Committee for UNICEF, 1968 (Box-folder 8: 8)
  - United States National Student Association, undated (Box-folder 8: 9)
  - United States State Department and Agency for International Development (AID), 1968-1969 (Box-folder 8: 10)
  - "University of Ibadan Plan for Relief Campaign,", 1970 (Box-folder 8: 11)
  - The War Cry, 1970 (Box-folder 8: 12)
  - West Africa, "Session or Security?,", 1969 (Box-folder 8: 13)
  - The World and the School, "Crisis Paper no. 7, The Nigerian Civil War: The Defeat of Biafra,", 1971 (Box-folder 8: 14)
  - "Zik in Lagos,", 1969 (Box-folder 8: 15)
- Photographs, undated
  - St. Louis Committee to Keep Biafra Alive, files I-III (54 photos) (Box 8)
  - Prints depicting sick and starving children in Biafra and Nigeria during the civil war (43 photos) (Envelope A)
- Memorabilia, undated
  - Biafran flag (Box 8)
- Sound Recordings, 1969, undated
  - "Susan Garth Biafran Babies' Appeal," recorded at the Hotel Barclay, New York, by Susan Garth, vinyl sound disc (33 1/3 LP) (Record cabinet)
  - "Civil War in Nigeria," World Horizons, Inc., 1969 (Record cabinet)
    Scope and Contents note
    A statement about the plight of people in war zone and relief work of churches, national anthems of Nigeria and Biafra, sounds from a marketplace in Biafra, and poem "Mother Dark" by Francesca Yetunda Pereira.
- Motion Pictures, undated
  - "The Biafran Tragedy," United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A., 16mm film (Film shelf)
  - "Twin Circle - Mary Umolu," 16mm film (Film shelf)